A Guide to the Emma Gray Trigg Papers 1920-1971
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Emma Gray Trigg Papers 1920-1971
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 40
4 linear feet
Emma Gray Trigg
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The bulk of the collection is a gift from Mrs. Trigg (1975-1977). A cassette tape of Mrs. Trigg reading Poetry (M 15) is the gift of Mrs. Donald Zimmerman.
Biographical/Historical Information
Emma Gray Trigg (1890-1976) was one of the prime movers behind the arts in Virginia. She was a leader, a promoter, and an major influence in the state's Fine Arts programs. She was also and artist in her own right.
Born in Norfolk, she attended Columbia and the University of Virginia. During the 1930s, she was director of a public relief program in Virginia that employed more than one hundred forty out-of-work musicians. During this time, Ms. Trigg was also a performer, giving several vocal recitals along the East Coast. In 1937, her first collection of verse, After Eden, was published receiving some critical attention.
For the duration of World War II she had the job of public information officer for the Office of Price Administration in Virginia. It was in this period that Ms. Trigg began to write a series of short children's plays and several operettas in collaboration with Elizabeth B. Maury. This eventually led to the adaptation of Mary Johnston's To Have and To Hold, which played successfully in Richmond during the 1950s.
In the late 1950s, Ms. Trigg was one of first to call for the formation of a symphony orchestra in Richmond; and after its institution, she served on its executive committee until the time of her death. She was also a past president of the Poetry Society of Virginia and a board member of the Poe Museum. Her second collection of poetry, The Paulonia Tree, was published in 1968.
Scope and Content Information
The Emma Gray (White) Trigg Papers (1920-1971) consist chiefly of drafts of her plays, "Julep Time," "The Lone Vixen," "To Have and To Hold" and "Greenbriar," and her book of poetry, The Spanish Pirates, together with some unpublished poetry and material about various materials.
Correspondence includes letters from fellow literary artists Max Eastman, James Branch Cabell, Ellen Glasgow, Harry M. Meacham, Marjorie K. Rawlings, Louis Untemeyer and Carl Van Vechten.
Photographs include one of Max Eastman and two of Carl Van Vechten.
SC and A also posses books from Trigg's library, including Peter Whiffle: His Life and Works by Van Vechten, which is inscribed to her.
Arrangement
Collection remains in the original order as received.
Contents List
- Julep-Time operetta in two acts, Music by Elizabeth (Box-folder 1.1)
- Score for Julep-Time by E.B. Maury (Box-folder 1.2)
- Larkspur an operetta in two acts, Music by E.B. Maury 1949 (Box-folder 1.3)
- Julep-Time character analysis for casting purposes (Box-folder 1.4)
- Julep-Time nearprint (Box-folder 1.5)
- Julep-Time with notes (Box-folder 1.6)
- Julep-Time programs, advertisements (Box-folder 1.7)
- Julep-Time Libretto score (Box-folder 1.8)
- The Greenbriar 1948 (Box-folder 1.9)
- The Greenbriar-Interlude (Box-folder 1.10)
- The Greenbriar-Synopsis (2) (Box-folder 1.11)
- The Greenbriar-with notes (Box-folder 1.12)
- The Greenbriar-revised version (Box-folder 1.13)
- The Greenbriar-revision after Richmond (Box-folder 1.14)
- Score for Julep-Time (Box-folder 1.15)
- Greenbriar-with revisions (Box-folder 1.16)
- Greenbriar-clippings and scrapbook (Box-folder 1.17)
- Poems written for John Powell (Box-folder 1a.1)
- Conservation on Poetry by Emma Gray Trigg and Florence Dickinson Stearn (Box-folder 1a.2)
- The Ballad of Four Players and other poetry (Box-folder 1a.3)
- After Eden (Box-folder 1a.4)
- Greenbriar-miscellaneous items (Box-folder 2.1)
- Greenbriar-photographs (Box-folder 2.2)
- Greenbriar-photos and advertisements (Box-folder 2.3)
- Lecture on War Poetry (Box-folder 2.4)
- The Van Lew Story-first revision (Box-folder 2.5)
- The Van Lew Story: the Lone Vixen (Box-folder 2.6)
- The Van Lew Story-scenes from Act III (Box-folder 2.7)
- The Lone Vixen-versions of Dhalgrens raid scene (Box-folder 2.8)
- The Lone Vixen (Box-folder 2.9)
- The Lone Vixen-with corrections (Box-folder 2.10)
- The Lone Vixen-with criticisms and changes (Box-folder 2.11)
- The Lone Vixen (Box-folder 2.12)
- The Lone Vixen-Act II scene 2 deleted from play (Box-folder 2.13)
- The Lone Vixen-newspaper clippings (Box-folder 2.14)
- The Lone Vixen-papers (Box-folder 2.15)
- Drafts of poems, lecturers, and a portion of The Lone Vixen, notebook (Box-folder 2.16)
- Richmond Symphony-papers, clippings (Box-folder 2a.1)
- Notebook of poems-EGT (Box-folder 2a.2)
- Scrapbook (Box-folder 2a.3)
- Newspaper clippings (Box-folder 2a.4)
- Poetry (Box-folder 2a.5)
- The Rainbow Has an End-a one act play (Box-folder 2a.6)
- Scraps of Magic-a one act play (Box-folder 2a.7)
- Scraps of Magic-score lyrics (Box-folder 2a.8)
- Spring's Around the Corner-a one act fairy play for children (Box-folder 2a.9)
- Spring's Around the Corner-miscellaneous materials (Box-folder 2a.10)
- To Have and to Hold-an operetta in two acts (Box-folder 2a.11)
- To Have and to Hold-miscellaneous materials for the production (Box-folder 2a.12)
- Letter from Mrs. Trigg to Hart School (Box-folder 2a.13)
- Correspondence, regarding research and publication of The Spanish Pirates1956 (Box-folder 3.1)
- Transcriptions of articles for research regarding The Spanish Pirates (Box-folder 3.2)
- Galley proofs, with corrections, The Spanish Pirates1973 (Box-folder 3.3)
- The Spanish Pirates-final draft and earlier revised pages (Box-folder 3.4)
- Research materials, regarding The Spanish Pirates1973 (Box-folder 3.5)
- To Have and to Hold, final corrections 1955 (Box-folder 3.6)
- Miscellaneous materials regarding To Have and to Hold (Box-folder 3.7)
- Newspaper clippings regarding To Have and To Hold (Box-folder 3.8)
- Miscellaneous writings by Emma Gray Trigg (Box-folder 3.9)
- Reviews by Emma Gray Trigg (Box-folder 3.10)
- Correspondence 1948-1976 (Box-folder 3.11)
  including letter from Mrs. Woodrow Wilson
- Correspondence 1948-1976 (Box-folder 3.12)
  including letters to Arthur Norris
- Correspondence of Richmond and Elizabeth Maury regarding Greenbriar (Box-folder 3.13)
- Miscellaneous correspondence and correspondents 1914-1974 (Box-folder 3.14)
  including letter from Hal Pierce
- Critique of Emma Gray Trigg by Clyde Hobbs Kincheloe (Box-folder 4.1)
- Clippings regarding Emma Gray Trigg (Box-folder 4.2)
- Diary notes of European excursion (Box-folder 4.3)
- Trigg concerts, programs, reviews, advertisements (Box-folder 4.4)
- Correspondence by E.G. Trigg regarding CWA Concerts (Box-folder 4.5)
- Correspondence by E.G. Trigg regarding CWA Music Project (Box-folder 4.6)
- Miscellaneous papers, correspondence regarding CWA Music Project 1933-1934 (Box-folder 4.7)
- Permit, programs for CWA Concerts (Box-folder 4.8)
- Contribution Lists, to Special Collections 1968-1975 (Box-folder 4.9)
- Miscellaneous clippings (Box-folder 4.10)
- Miscellaneous materials regarding Poetry Society of Virginia and Poetry Society Collection (Box-folder 4.11)
- Miscellaneous items (Box-folder 4.12)
- Photographs, concert performers, Emma Gray Trigg (Box-folder 4.13)
- Nearprint, Intellectual Life in Nineteenth Century Richmond, by Maurice Duke (Box-folder 4.14)
- Introduction for Parke Rouse by Harry Woodward (Box-folder 4.15)
- Nearprint, On Human Nature and Survival by Paul Note 1970 (Box-folder 4.16)
- Score and Lyrics from The Green Thumb (Box-folder 5.1)
- A Green Thumb (Box-folder 5.2)
- Manuscript poetry (Box-folder 5.3)
- The Rainbow Has An End (Box-folder 5.4)
- Scrapes of Magic (Box-folder 5.5)
- Score and Lyrics for Scrape of Magic (Box-folder 5.6)
- Spring's Around the Corner (Box-folder 5.7)
- Misc. materials of Spring's Around the Corner (Box-folder 5.8)
- To Have and to Hold, typed manuscript (Box-folder 5.9)
- misc. manuscripts To Have and to Hold (Box-folder 5.10)
- manuscripts Re: Production of To Have and to Hold (Box-folder 5.11)
- Eastman, Max 1937-1939 (Box-folder 6.1)
- Eastman, Max 1940-1945 (Box-folder 6.2)
- Eastman, Max 1951-1961 (Box-folder 6.3)
- Eastman, Max, n.d. (Box-folder 6.4)
  Including a letter dated 6/29/71 from Trigg to Gerald McCabe, of the VCU Libraries regarding her relationship to Eastman
- Letter from Trigg regarding Eastman's views on Russia (Box-folder 6.5)
- Cabell, James Branch 1937-1938 (Box-folder 6.6)
- Dillon, George 1937-1961 (Box-folder 6.7)
- Glasgow, Ellen, n.d. 1931, 1942, 1945 (Box-folder 6.8)
- Meacham, Harry M. 1972-1975 (Box-folder 6.9)
- Rawlings, Marjorie K. (Box-folder 6.10)
- Untemeyer, Louis 1940-1973 (Box-folder 6.11)
- Van Vechten, Carl 1937 (Box-folder 6.12)
  copies of letters from Van Vechten to Trigg made by Edgar MacDonald covering the years 1923-24 and a letter about the letters from Trigg dated 1959
- Miscellaneous correspondence (Box-folder 6.12)
- Miscellaneous clippings and material (Box-folder 6.13)
- Miscellaneous papers, correspondence (Box-folder 6.14)
- Photographs (Box-folder 6.15)
  including: Doris Holmes - 1955, John Holmes - 1956, John L. Holmes - 1955, Margaret Freeman Cabell, Emma Gray Trigg & Martha Richford Roberts - 1973, Emma Gray White - 1914, Carl Van Vechten and Farina Marinoff - 1924, Carl Van Vecthten - 1927, Joseph Herghesmer - 1923, Max Eastman - taken by Carl Van Vechten, and 1939